<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>comparative phylogenetics on HCL | Life History Evolution</title>
    <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/tags/comparative-phylogenetics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in comparative phylogenetics on HCL | Life History Evolution</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.christophliedtke.com/tags/comparative-phylogenetics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reproductive Mode Evolution</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/reproductive_modes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/reproductive_modes/</guid>
      <description>I am interested in understanding of how parts or all of the ancestral biphasic life cycle of amphibians has been lost or modified. I use comparative phylogenetic methods to study how life history modes have evolved and how this may impact on lineage diversification. I am also interested in what may have driven the evolution of terrestrial modes of reproduction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome Size Evolution</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/genome_size/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/genome_size/</guid>
      <description>Genome Size Evolution Genomes of different organisms vary hugely in size. Most of this difference is not linked to organism complexity, but instead, in the amount of non-coding DNA. Whether or not life history traits affect the evolution of the physical size of genomes is unclear. On a cellular level, large genomes impose physiological rate limits and processes like cell proliferation and differentiation are significantly slower. This is particularly important for amphibians, which have some of the largest genomes of all known vertebrates and many undergo complex life history transitions that involve both rapid growth as well as cell and tissue differentiation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
