<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HCL | Life History Evolution</title>
    <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on HCL | Life History Evolution</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 18:19:33 +0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.christophliedtke.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Pigmentation Plasticity</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/pigmentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/pigmentation/</guid>
      <description>An organism’s capacity to track and resemble its background (‘background matching’) is an important cryptic mechanism in the animal kingdom. Some species have evolved facultative colour change, a remarkable form of phenotypic plasticity, to match temporally or spatially heterogeneous backgrounds. Here, we quantify the capacity of such facultative changes in pigmentation in Western Spadefoot tadpoles (Pelobates cultripes), by manipulating the background colour of aquaria. We find that tadpoles of this species are capable of detecting and responding to even minor changes in background brightness by adjusting the pigmentation content in their skin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproductive Mode Evolution</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/reproductive_modes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/reproductive_modes/</guid>
      <description>I am interested in understanding of how parts or all of the ancestral biphasic life cycle of amphibians has been lost or modified. I use comparative phylogenetic methods to study how life history modes have evolved and how this may impact on lineage diversification. I am also interested in what may have driven the evolution of terrestrial modes of reproduction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amphibian Systematics</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/amphibian_systematics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/amphibian_systematics/</guid>
      <description>Amphibian Systematics A great deal of work needs to be done to update the taxonomy and systematics of African amphibians and to gain a deeper understanding about aspects of their natural history. Recent years, perhaps fuelled by the proliferation of molecular barcoding techniques coupled with phylogenetic and coalescence species delimitation methods, have seen a surge in systematic revisions and newly described species. Together with many colleagues, I have contributed to furthering our understanding of species, their distributions, biogeography and natural history for a number of African amphibians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Full CV</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/cv/curr_vit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 12:27:38 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/cv/curr_vit/</guid>
      <description>I am an evolutionary biologist currently based at the Biological Station of Doñana, in Spain. Read my full CV here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Publication List</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/pubs_iframe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 12:27:38 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/pubs_iframe/</guid>
      <description>iframe test</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tanzania: The Ukaguru Report</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/ukaguru_report/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 12:29:40 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/ukaguru_report/</guid>
      <description>Background “There was something deep under the bark of this tree… I couldn’t believe I even spotted it”. This is how Michele Menegon described his encounter with the Beautiful Forest Toad, some fifteen years ago, only two years after it was even discovered. And that was probably the last anyone (at least anyone who cared) saw it. In a time when the news seems to paint a bleak picture for what’s in store for biodiversity on our planet, rediscoveries of creatures thought extinct shine through like the feel-good stories we need right now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developmental Plasticity</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/pc_transcriptomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/pc_transcriptomics/</guid>
      <description>Larval Developmental Acceleration Developmental plasticity is a common adaptation to environmental heterogeneity and understanding the evolution of such plasticity is an important goal in evolutionary biology. Amphibian larvae are usually capable of accelerating their development in response to pond drying to avoid desiccation risk, with the Western Spadefoot toad (Pelobates cultripes) being an extreme example. This species can accelerate its development by more than 30%! The Gomez Mestre Group is currently working on uncovering the gene regulatory network underlying this plasticity, by experimentally induce early development through simulated pond drying and screen the transcriptome for differentially expressed genes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome Size Evolution</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/genome_size/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/genome_size/</guid>
      <description>Genome Size Evolution Genomes of different organisms vary hugely in size. Most of this difference is not linked to organism complexity, but instead, in the amount of non-coding DNA. Whether or not life history traits affect the evolution of the physical size of genomes is unclear. On a cellular level, large genomes impose physiological rate limits and processes like cell proliferation and differentiation are significantly slower. This is particularly important for amphibians, which have some of the largest genomes of all known vertebrates and many undergo complex life history transitions that involve both rapid growth as well as cell and tissue differentiation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Malawi: The Golden Squeaker of Mt. Mulanje</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/malawi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2012 12:29:40 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/malawi/</guid>
      <description>Biogeographically, Malawi is interesting. We know a lot about East Africa and Southern Africa, but Malawi somehow falls in the middle, and no one is really sure whether the animals in its forests are close relatives to East African animals or Southern African animals. There is the Nyika Plateau in the north that somehow feels like it could be an extension of the Tanzanian Eastern Arc Mountain rifting, and then there is the peculiar Mulanje Massive in the south, that, rising like Inselbergs, seem to have more in common with Mozambican highlands, but do the animals that live there tell the same tale?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cameroon: The Hunt for the Egg Frogs</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/cameroon/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 12:29:40 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/cameroon/</guid>
      <description>..yes.. egg frogs. Not the most appealing name (apparently named after their oval-shaped bodies), but they are fantastic little creatures. Distributed across Central and parts of West Africa, some 15 species make up the genus Leptodactylodon. Although they are usually fairly inconspicuous, earth-toned frogs, turn them over and you will find brilliant spots and sometimes even bizarre ossifications in males that stick out of their chest.
 Dull, leaf-litter colours on top, bright blue spots below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rwanda: The Land of a Thousand Hills</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/rwanda/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2011 12:29:40 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/rwanda/</guid>
      <description>They call Rwanda the land of a thousand hills, and they weren&amp;rsquo;t kidding&amp;hellip;.
It&amp;rsquo;s one of the smallest country in Africa (smaller even than most European countries, clocking in just behind Belgium), that unfortunately has one of the most devastating recent histories. The genocide of 1994, was one of the most brutal the modern world has seen and one the international community has to bear the cross for in many respects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communicating with Carpenter Bees in Kenya</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/kenya/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2009 12:29:40 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/blog/kenya/</guid>
      <description>Semiochemicals: chemicals used by organisms for the purpose of communication. Never heard of them? You certainly have, but under different names&amp;hellip; Pheromones are in fact a type of semiochemical that are used to communicate with members of the same species. But there are more. Organisms can also communicate between species using chemical cues. Flowers for example, smell nice because they want to attract pollinators. The chemicals produced in this scenario are often called allomones because they are beneficial to the originator, but they may also act as kairomones, which are chemical cues that are beneficial for the receiver, that is, IF the flower provides a nectar reward.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
