<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>amphibians on HCL | Life History Evolution</title>
    <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/tags/amphibians/</link>
    <description>Recent content in amphibians on HCL | Life History Evolution</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.christophliedtke.com/tags/amphibians/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reproductive Mode Evolution</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/reproductive_modes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/reproductive_modes/</guid>
      <description>I am interested in understanding of how parts or all of the ancestral biphasic life cycle of amphibians has been lost or modified. I use comparative phylogenetic methods to study how life history modes have evolved and how this may impact on lineage diversification. I am also interested in what may have driven the evolution of terrestrial modes of reproduction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amphibian Systematics</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/amphibian_systematics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/amphibian_systematics/</guid>
      <description>Amphibian Systematics A great deal of work needs to be done to update the taxonomy and systematics of African amphibians and to gain a deeper understanding about aspects of their natural history. Recent years, perhaps fuelled by the proliferation of molecular barcoding techniques coupled with phylogenetic and coalescence species delimitation methods, have seen a surge in systematic revisions and newly described species. Together with many colleagues, I have contributed to furthering our understanding of species, their distributions, biogeography and natural history for a number of African amphibians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome Size Evolution</title>
      <link>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/genome_size/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.christophliedtke.com/portfolio/genome_size/</guid>
      <description>Genome Size Evolution Genomes of different organisms vary hugely in size. Most of this difference is not linked to organism complexity, but instead, in the amount of non-coding DNA. Whether or not life history traits affect the evolution of the physical size of genomes is unclear. On a cellular level, large genomes impose physiological rate limits and processes like cell proliferation and differentiation are significantly slower. This is particularly important for amphibians, which have some of the largest genomes of all known vertebrates and many undergo complex life history transitions that involve both rapid growth as well as cell and tissue differentiation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
